<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://microbiology.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://microbiology.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-11-01T15:33:07-05:00</updated><id>http://microbiology.github.io/</id><title type="html">Prophage</title><subtitle>The Blog for Bacteria, Phages, Computers, and Science</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Five Key Considerations When Building A Data Science Team</title><link href="http://microbiology.github.io/blog/BuildingDSTeam/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Five Key Considerations When Building A Data Science Team" /><published>2020-11-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-11-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://microbiology.github.io/blog/BuildingDSTeam</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://microbiology.github.io/blog/BuildingDSTeam/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point it’s a familiar problem. Companies, organizations, and other groups have continued to grapple with how to extract more value from their data, and leveraging information more effectively. Here enters &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Data_science&quot;&gt;data science&lt;/a&gt;, the broad field dedicated to extracting information and insight from data using statistics, engineering, subject matter expertise, etc. The increasing availability of data and computing power has been a major driver for the field in recent years, and data science departments have continued to pop up in organizations and companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While most groups see value in data science, many have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wired.com/story/companies-rushing-use-ai-few-see-payoff/&quot;&gt;struggled to extract a return on their data science investment&lt;/a&gt;. This has therefore continued to be an intense area of discussion and exploration across industries, with everyone trying to understand how data science can be more effectively used to create value. As a result, discussions have been moving away from general sentiments around “let’s just hire some data scientists”, to more strategic and informed actions. I have likewise been conversing and thinking around this fascinating challenge, and aim to organize some of those thoughts here (note that this is certainly not a complete list). In this post, we will explore what it takes to build and empower data science teams, and highlight some of the many resources available on this topic. Of course there are other important topics here, such as how we can effectively leverage an existing data science team, and what projects we should be focusing on, but we will focus on those in other posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;define-data-scientist-before-building&quot;&gt;1. Define “Data Scientist” Before Building&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When having a discussion, it’s often helpful to define our terms (ask Voltaire) and the data science space is no different. As many of us know, the terms “data science” and “data scientist” are often ambiguous. It seems as if you can ask ten people to define “data science” and get about ten different answers. In the context of building a data science team, it’s therefore critical to define the data science skills, goals, and ambitions so that everyone can be united and work toward the same vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the Harvard Business Review and others have articulated well, there are &lt;a href=&quot;https://hbr.org/2018/11/the-kinds-of-data-scientist&quot;&gt;many types of data scientists and data roles&lt;/a&gt;, and it’s important to understand who is required when building a data science team. We can ask ourselves whether the requirements are focused on statistics, engineering databases, engineering graphic user interfaces, software engineering, or  driving research that requires expertise in a subject matter (e.g. chemistry). Most often an effective team will require members of diverse backgrounds to work together, so the right combinations will be important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../images/netlifx-ds-skill-examples.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Example illustration for some different types of data science skill sets to consider when building a team. &lt;a href=&quot;https://netflixtechblog.com/notebook-innovation-591ee3221233&quot;&gt;Netflix source.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;strategize-around-data-science-structure--team-integration&quot;&gt;2. Strategize Around Data Science Structure &amp;amp; Team Integration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to thinking about the composition of the team, it’s equally important to think about where they will be in the larger organization (university, company, or other type of group). I think Accenture does a nice job of presenting the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.accenture.com/us-en/~/media/accenture/conversion-assets/dotcom/documents/global/pdf/industries_2/accenture-building-analytics-driven-organization.pdf&quot;&gt;different options for implementing data science (what they call an analytics organization structure)&lt;/a&gt;. To simplify the landscape, these options offer varying degrees of coordination, flexibility, and resourcing. In an unappealing &lt;em&gt;decentralized model&lt;/em&gt;, the resources will be allocated to parochial and potentially ineffective initiatives while in a more appealing &lt;em&gt;centralized&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;center of excellence&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;federated model&lt;/em&gt;, the teams can be more effectively aligned with organizational strategies while remaining flexible and collaborative. There are a lot of ways to draw out how our teams will fit into the bigger picture, and this is an important consideration with a lot of components, so we need to remember to spend some time on this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../images/AccentureExamples.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Options for organizing data science teams within a larger organization. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.accenture.com/us-en/~/media/accenture/conversion-assets/dotcom/documents/global/pdf/industries_2/accenture-building-analytics-driven-organization.pdf&quot;&gt;Accenture source.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;invest-in-organized--accessible-data&quot;&gt;3. Invest in Organized &amp;amp; Accessible Data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more obvious aspect of building a data science team is hiring people with relevant expertise, but ensuring they have the tools they need can be an after thought. I’ve had many conversations with people from various research groups/organizations that have experienced hiring data science teams, only to have them asking for proper infrastructure and data access. It’s therefore critical to anticipate investing in, and supporting the needs of, data science teams which will include &lt;strong&gt;computing infrastructure&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;access to data&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This also ties into the point around team skills. For example, having some data engineers on a team can be really helpful for working through databasing problems and streamlining areas like statistics. Having managers to help with governance and compliance can also be helpful. Of course there is no one-size-fits-all formula, but spending some time thinking this through can really help a data science group thrive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;establish-a-collaborative-analysis-infrastructure&quot;&gt;4. Establish A Collaborative Analysis Infrastructure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collaboration&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;transparency&lt;/strong&gt; are key to any scientific endeavor, including data science. This is especially true at an organizational level. It’s important to think about how members of a data science team will share their results with each other, how they will share results outside of their group, and how they will evaluate the work of their teammates (e.g. code review). The Netflix data science folks articulate this well and &lt;a href=&quot;https://netflixtechblog.com/notebook-innovation-591ee3221233&quot;&gt;identify frameworks resources such as Jupyter Notebooks for facilitating transparency and collaboration&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../images/netflix-example-scheme.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Example flowchart for building an effective analytic platform to empower data science teams. This diagram includes the notebooking tools, compute platforms, sharing resources, and databases. &lt;a href=&quot;https://netflixtechblog.com/notebook-innovation-591ee3221233&quot;&gt;Netflix source.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jupyter.org&quot;&gt;Jupyter notebooks (similar to R Markdown and notebooks)&lt;/a&gt; are tools that allow analytical data scientists to incorporate &lt;em&gt;contextual language&lt;/em&gt; (such as introductions or interpretations) with the &lt;em&gt;analytical code&lt;/em&gt; (including rendered figures, tables, etc). This type of notebook environment can be integrated with coding tools like git, computing resources like AWS, organizational databases for each and reproducible data access, and notebook sharing tools (see the Netflix blog post for details). Integrating all of these tools together can really streamline the work of a data science team, sort of like providing a team of builders with power tools. Implementing a strong infrastructure goes a long way in ensuring the success of a data science team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;be-agile--keep-improving&quot;&gt;5. Be Agile &amp;amp; Keep Improving&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we have mentioned above, there is no one-size-fits-all solution to building an effective data science teams. That being said, there is one practice that can likely help improve the odds of successfully implementing a data science team (or probably any type of team), and that is to remain Agile. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agile_software_development&quot;&gt;Agile is a development philosophy&lt;/a&gt; that encourages frequent feedback and improvements on projects. To remain Agile while building and maintaining a data science group means we should continue to get feedback from team members and collaborators, figure out what’s working and what’s not, and change course as needed. We can’t be afraid to experiment and try new things, not just at the start but continually. If anything, this type of mindfulness will improve our odds at building a successful team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many organization have been building out data science teams, and as mentioned above, they have been met with varying success. In this post, we explored what it might take to build a successful data science team, and we identified five key areas of consideration. Of course this is not a complete list, and there are many other important components to building successful data science teams. However a brief review of existing literature leads us to focusing on at least 1) defining data science roles, 2) strategizing on team integration, 3) investing in adequate resources, 4) building out a notebook analysis infrastructure, and 5) remaining Agile through the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, I definitely encourage interested reads to check out the linked material above, because we are only scratching the surface in this post. And of course, please let me know if you have any questions, comments, or concerns in the comment section below.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Data Science" /><category term="Strategy" /><summary type="html">Building a data science team is hard. Here we explore what may lead to success.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Learning To Code With Problem-Based Group Learning &amp;amp; LeetCode</title><link href="http://microbiology.github.io/blog/CodeClubAndLeetCode/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Learning To Code With Problem-Based Group Learning &amp; LeetCode" /><published>2020-09-13T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-09-13T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://microbiology.github.io/blog/CodeClubAndLeetCode</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://microbiology.github.io/blog/CodeClubAndLeetCode/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning to code can be challenging, especially getting started. On the flip side, it can be challenging to know how to facilitate meaningful code education in groups, especially in this age of virtual meetings instead of doing things in-person. There are a lot of ways to go about it, including workshops, lectures, courses, open coding hours, and code reviews. Last week our group tried using the online platform &lt;strong&gt;LeetCode&lt;/strong&gt; as a way to bring together our research site (all with different levels of programming skills) to learn some Python by solving a problem together. This was a different use of an hour, departing from our usual workshop style, but it ended up being really effective. This week we will discuss the problem-based approach to learning Python in a virtual group setting, and hopefully others can use this as a starting point for their own coding sessions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our virtual group code session followed a pretty simple agenda. We began with an introduction to some important Python concepts, then we broke into small groups (about 3-4 people) which all included at least one proficient coder (like a TA). After working together to solve the problem, we all came back and shared our findings. We were able to accomplish this all in an hour, but it was honestly a tight hour. If you expect a lot of question in the intro, or if you suspect the teams will need a lot of time, then you may want to allocate an hour and a half to be safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Introduction to Basic Python Concepts - &lt;em&gt;20 minutes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Problem Solving In Breakout Groups - &lt;em&gt;25 minutes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Breakout Groups Present Their Learnings - &lt;em&gt;15 minutes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;starting-with-basic-python-concepts&quot;&gt;Starting With Basic Python Concepts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the group ranged from beginners to experts, we started with a brief introduction of some foundational Python concepts (variables, lists, and for loops) to help get us all on the same page. &lt;a href=&quot;../../../pdfs_etc/PythonCodeClubIntro-20200911.pdf&quot;&gt;The PowerPoint presentation we used can be found here&lt;/a&gt;. This presentation was crafted to specifically cover all of the concepts required to solve the problem, with one key omission. Our introduction did not include the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;return&lt;/code&gt; function, which is required to obtain a successful output in LeetCode. In the introductory presentation, we mentioned the value of “Googling questions” and this prompted the groups to find the answer on their own. After concluding the intro and taking a couple questions, we broke into breakout groups to solve the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem-solving-in-breakout-groups&quot;&gt;Problem Solving In Breakout Groups&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the introduction to some basic Python concepts, we set out to solve our Python problem. We all attempted to solve LeetCode problem &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;1480&lt;/code&gt;, which is titled &lt;a href=&quot;https://leetcode.com/problems/running-sum-of-1d-array/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Calculating the Running Sum Of A 1d Array&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. After revealing the problem to the large group, we broke into breakout groups of 3-4 people. This can be challenging to do virtually, so make sure to check out your video chat capabilities ahead of time. We also made sure to have a dedicated lead for each breakout group, who was experienced with coding but mostly facilitated the problem-solving of the group, and making sure everyone gets the chance to participate. The LeetCode problem we chose was pretty straightforward and most groups were able to solve it in the time provided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../images/leetcode_example.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Screen shot of the LeetCode example we used. The problem is stated on the left, and the users can code on the right. All of the coding can be done in the right panel, which avoids issues with installations, dependencies, and the dreaded “Mac vs PC” battle.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During this session, we found that it’s important to &lt;strong&gt;focus on the learning&lt;/strong&gt; and not just solving the problem. Solving a problem under time constraints can be stressful and this might encourage groups to rush through concepts instead of learning together, among other things. The goal of this is the journey, not the destination, so it was important for us to really focus on learning here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;breakout-groups-present-their-learnings&quot;&gt;Breakout Groups Present Their Learnings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After everyone regrouped, we all shared our learnings with each other. Again, it’s okay that not everyone reaches a solution. The focus on the group presentations was to share what was learned, and to provide some exposure of those learnings to the other groups. In the interest of time, we had one member present from each group, and each group both 1) showed their resulting code and 2) shared something interesting that they learned. This also showed that many different code approaches can be used to accomplish the same goal. We also collected the code from each group and provided it to everyone after, so that they can reference it again if needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This event was a different style for our big research group, but we had a lot of fun with it. By focusing on solving a problem together, we were able to all stay engaged, figure things out, and ultimately have a memorable experience. We also introduced everyone to the extensive LeetCode platform, which provides a lot of follow up problems for attendees to try when continuing to learn Python on their own. I would definitely recommend this approach for other research groups, especially those with large groups like ours (we are ~50 people total). Remember to have fun with it, and don’t hesitate to drop A question in the comment section below!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Python" /><category term="Learning To Code" /><category term="Education" /><category term="Code" /><summary type="html">Our site recently got together to learn some Python through solving a problem.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Impact of Bacterial Viruses on Cancer Immunity</title><link href="http://microbiology.github.io/blog/PhageAndCancerTreatment/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Impact of Bacterial Viruses on Cancer Immunity" /><published>2020-08-29T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-08-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://microbiology.github.io/blog/PhageAndCancerTreatment</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://microbiology.github.io/blog/PhageAndCancerTreatment/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back at this blog, it’s been a YEAR since my last post?! And it’s been an eventful year, both personally and globally. But today I’m excited to discuss a different kind of virus than what we usually here about these days. The virus for discussion today is the bacteriophage, which is a type of virus that only infects and kills bacteria, and not humans or other animals. Here we will focus on some exciting recent work by Fluckiger &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;, which implicated a specific bacterial virus as a facilitator of cancer treatment efficacy and immunity. In this post, we will first review the findings of paper, and then speculate on some potential follow up work and the implications of the findings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past couple of years, the microbiome has been implicated as a potentially important factor in cancer treatment and immunity, especially in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Checkpoint_inhibitor&quot;&gt;immune checkpoint inhibitor therapy (ICI)&lt;/a&gt;. This has included work from Routy &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;, Tanoue &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;, and others. What is particularly interesting in these papers is that they don’t always agree on the specific microbiome factors impacting ICI response. Some papers suggest one species is important, and another implicates another species or group of species. While this could suggest a need for more uniform analysis across the studies, it could also suggest there is another underlying commonality, or otherwise missing feature, that implicates the microbiome in ICI response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;linking-phages-to-cancer-immunity&quot;&gt;Linking Phages To Cancer Immunity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group of Fluckiger &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt; began their work with an interesting observation. In their model for cancer treatment (in this case it’s chemotherapy, not ICI), they found that the presence of some &lt;em&gt;E. hirae&lt;/em&gt; bacterial strains resulted in more effective chemotherapy compared to other bacterial strains. They asked what the underlying mechanism could be to explain such variability between strains. To answer this, they performed a series of targeted follow up experiments and identified a &lt;strong&gt;bacteriophage tape measure protein&lt;/strong&gt; (TMP1 to be exact), which was integrated in the &lt;em&gt;E. hirae&lt;/em&gt; genome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../images/ici_phage_response.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Manuscript figure that shows the TMP1 phage signal may be associated with improved cancer ICI outcome. While this is interesting, more work will be required to determine whether this is actually clinically relevant.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now this is an interesting finding. Some bacterial strains were effective at improving chemotherapy efficacy because of a bacteriophage infection, and not the bacterium itself. In this case, the TMP1 is a common gene used by bacteriophages in their tail construction process. Both capsids (the heads) and tails of bacteriophages can cause an immune response, and the authors actually found that the improved chemotherapy efficacy was associated with cytotoxic T cell activity (immune cells that kill dangerous cells).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this work suggested that the phages were improving an immune response against cancer cells, and the authors hypothesized that it was due to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Molecular_mimicry&quot;&gt;molecular mimicry&lt;/a&gt;. Molecular mimicry occurs when microbial or other foreign antigens are similar to a host (e.g. human) protein and cause the immune system to mount a response to itself. As expected, the authors ran a DNA alignment analysis and found that the TMP1 immunogenic region was similar to &lt;strong&gt;PSMB4&lt;/strong&gt;, and mammalian gene that is over-expressed in many cancer cells. After additional work, the authors confirmed that the bacteriophages are improving chemotherapy response by “mimicking” genes found in the cancer cells, and activating the immune system to attack and kill the cancer cells more effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all of these results, it’s hard to not wonder whether this response holds true for ICI, and not just chemotherapy. The authors of this work did not dive into this question in detail, but they did end the paper by showing that in a single clinical cohort, the presence of the TMP phage was associated with improved ICI therapeutic outcome (see figure above). In other words, it appeared that patients with the TMP phage survived longer than patients without the phage. While this is interesting and encouraging, extensive additional work will be needed to tease this out and understand the clinical implications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;possible-future-directions&quot;&gt;Possible Future Directions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the exciting aspects of this paper is thinking about the directions this can go in next. One question I asked as I read this paper was whether this bacteriophage sequence can be found in other bacteria. The authors show us that the phage sequence is found in &lt;em&gt;E. gallinarum&lt;/em&gt;, but are there others? I actually went back and performed a BLAST DNA alignment with the TMP1 antigenic sequence &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;TSLARFANI&lt;/code&gt; to see what other bacteria contained the sequence. The alignment showed that the bacteriophage sequence is actually found in many different &lt;em&gt;Enterococcus&lt;/em&gt; bacteria. It also appeared in a &lt;em&gt;Listeria&lt;/em&gt; bacterium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../images/blast_phage_ici.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Results of a simple BLAST DNA alignment to bacteria using the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;TSLARFANI&lt;/code&gt; sequence.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, it will be interesting to see whether this and other groups follow up on understanding the association of TMP1 with ICI. Perhaps there is a unifying TMP1 signal across previous studies, which wouldn’t be apparent given the analyses done to date. It also begs the question of how antibiotics are associated with the microbiome and cancer treatment efficacy. We know that antibiotics might be associated with ICI efficacy, and they are also associated with bacteriophage activity. This begs the question of whether the two are connected. Finally, it will be interesting to see follow up work to evaluate whether the described signals could be used as therapeutic biomarkers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall this was a really cool study, and it has a lot of results to sift through. I definitely recommend checking it out for more details. It is also going to be incredibly exciting to watch how researchers follow up on this work. This work opens up many more questions of how the microbiome impacts cancer therapy and the immune system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did I miss anything, or do you have questions, comments, or concerns? Drop a message in the comments below and let’s get the conversation going.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Microbiology" /><category term="Recent Publications" /><category term="Oncology" /><category term="Microbiome" /><summary type="html">Bacteriophage molecular mimicry impacts chemotherapy and immunotherapy efficacy.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Doing Group Science With The Agile Methodology</title><link href="http://microbiology.github.io/blog/WorkingAgile/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Doing Group Science With The Agile Methodology" /><published>2019-09-02T15:08:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-02T15:08:00-04:00</updated><id>http://microbiology.github.io/blog/WorkingAgile</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://microbiology.github.io/blog/WorkingAgile/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been about two years since I began doing research at a pharmaceutical company, following my postdoctoral fellowship in academia. One big change was going from a role of doing science, into a role that involved more managing science in addition to doing science (this might be similar to the changes my young academic PI colleagues face). This seems to be especially key in industry settings because the science is generally more team-based. While I still do science, I find myself needing to manage larger groups of individuals around a project. This comes with its own learning curve and skill set. As I continue down this path, I wanted to reflect a little on this transition and some tips I have found useful. Hopefully others find these somewhat helpful as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to managing larger project groups, I think us biologists (either on the wet or dry side of the lab) can learn a lot from our software engineering colleagues. One of the most influential skills I have learned has been the ability to do scientific research using an Agile/SCRUM approach. There is a lot to working in an Agile/SCRUM framework (you can read the foundational philosophies &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agile_software_development&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), but this sort of framework has ended up working pretty well for the groups I am involved in, and I want to share some of my experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three basic components to effectively work in this type of Agile environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;using-a-kanban-board&quot;&gt;1. Using a Kanban Board&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kanban board is a tool for managing tasks and progress. It is essentially a todo list of tasks that are organized into a couple columns that reflect the progress of each task. In my groups, we use four columns for measuring progress: &lt;strong&gt;The backlog&lt;/strong&gt;, which holds tasks that we are not currently working on, but will later; the tasks that are &lt;strong&gt;in progress&lt;/strong&gt;, the tasks that are being &lt;strong&gt;reviewed&lt;/strong&gt; (e.g. a completed experiment that the rest of the group is looking over), and the &lt;strong&gt;completed tasks&lt;/strong&gt;. By assigning each task to a &lt;em&gt;team member&lt;/em&gt;, a &lt;em&gt;topic&lt;/em&gt; (the bigger part of the project that the task fits in to), a &lt;em&gt;priority&lt;/em&gt;, and a &lt;em&gt;description&lt;/em&gt;, you can easily track the progress of the team toward completing the goals of the project (and because this is science,  there is room to change course when we learn new information). This works as a nice “guiding star” for the group, and can help other team members know what the others are working on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../images/agile_kanban_example.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A generic example of a Kanban board for managing tasks. The tasks move from the todo list on the left, to the complete column on the right.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://trello.com&quot;&gt;Trello&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; are commonly used tools for managing Kanban boards. Our group uses &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.atlassian.com/software/jira&quot;&gt;JIRA&lt;/a&gt;, but there are a lot available out there so you can try them out and see which you and your team like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;standup-meetings&quot;&gt;2. Standup Meetings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have found &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stand-up_meeting&quot;&gt;standup meetings&lt;/a&gt; to be crucial to our teamwork, but it is a meeting type that is not commonly known. The idea behind standup meetings is that they are regular meetings (every day, week, or whatever) in which everyone remains standing, which prevents members from getting comfortable and keeps things moving quickly. I have found success in holding these meetings for a half hour every other week. We usually go through the Kanban board, with each task getting a progress report from the person to which the task was assigned. These efficient meetings both give the group an overview of how the entire team is progressing, but also provides an opportunity to identify areas that require additional conversation or help from other members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sprinting-science&quot;&gt;3. Sprinting Science&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After working for a few months through the above framework (Kanban boards and standup meetings), we encountered an issue of prioritization. It’s easy to assign somebody ten different tasks, but the workload can quickly become overwhelming and everything can move forward slowly. As a way to mitigate this issue, I have found success in embracing the “sprinting” philosophy from SCRUM, in which we keep our expectations to prioritizing what can be accomplished in a single two-week period. Usually this ends up looking like somebody being assigned two or three tasks for an upcoming two-week spring, but it depends on what your tasks look like (quick software updates will take less time than long &lt;em&gt;in vitro&lt;/em&gt; cell culturing experiments). These few tasks ultimately become the primary topics of the next standup meeting because those are the main areas that were worked on between the two meetings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By putting these three practices together, teams can work really effectively together to push the group’s science forward. The &lt;strong&gt;Kanban board&lt;/strong&gt; serves as a guiding light for the group  and measures group progress, the &lt;strong&gt;standup meetings&lt;/strong&gt; provide a way to review team progress and identify areas to help each other, and embracing a &lt;strong&gt;sprinting mentality&lt;/strong&gt; keeps tasks prioritized on what can be realistically done in the next short window of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are just some basic ideas for how this can all work, but they have seemed to work well in my experience. If you are wondering how to effectively manage your group’s science, hopefully some of these principles will also be useful. Any thoughts on how this could work better, or questions on the topic? Leave a comment or reach out on social media or email. I always love hearing from readers!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Organization" /><category term="Science" /><category term="Project Management" /><summary type="html">Three helpful tips for managing large science projects using Agile/SCRUM.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Empowering Science Through Organization (Bullet Journals)</title><link href="http://microbiology.github.io/blog/BulletJournal/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Empowering Science Through Organization (Bullet Journals)" /><published>2019-06-16T21:25:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-16T21:25:00-04:00</updated><id>http://microbiology.github.io/blog/BulletJournal</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://microbiology.github.io/blog/BulletJournal/">&lt;p&gt;Some challenges we can face as scientist are not just our experiments and analyses, but keeping organized and balancing the hundreds of things we have to do each day. There are lots of tools out there for keeping on top of our todo lists, but if you are like me, you have found it difficult to actually find one that sticks, and actually improves day-to-day life. After trying many different approaches and tools, I’ve really come to like the bullet journal strategy. Because I have found it to be such a game changer, I want to break away from the research heavy topics and share some of my experiences in how I’ve better enabled my science by improving my organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../images/RapidLogExample.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Example comparison of a “traditional” todo list compared to a “rapid logging” bullet journal approach, taken from the Bullet Journal website.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned above, I’ve tried different organizational approaches including standard todo lists (including PostIt notes) and kanban boards like on GitHub. I had tried Trello for managing tasks, and I’d tried the Apple todo list thing that comes standard on their machines. After going through these various tools, I  never actually found something that worked. For a while I was relying on sticky notes, my calendar, flagged emails, and other random techniques to keep track of what I needed to do, and it was kind of a pain. Then I came across the &lt;em&gt;bullet journal&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting started with a Bullet Journal is pretty simple, and you can get most of the relevant information &lt;a href=&quot;https://bulletjournal.com/pages/learn&quot;&gt;online here&lt;/a&gt;. This approach to keeping todo lists emphasizes simplicity, as well as modularity, meaning you can use the parts you like and exclude the parts you don’t. I have found the simplicity and modularity to be important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main idea behind Bullet Journaling is that you &lt;strong&gt;keep a running log of you tasks&lt;/strong&gt; as bullet points (marked with a &lt;em&gt;simple dot&lt;/em&gt;). You can make notes with &lt;em&gt;dashes&lt;/em&gt; and events with &lt;em&gt;open cirlces&lt;/em&gt;, but most of my bullet journal is tasks. I use notes sparingly and never use the events feature (they just never really worked for me). I also usually nest my notes under their related tasks. I use a star to prioritize tasks, I draw an “X” over a task dot when it is completed, I draw a “&quot; when I need to transfer the task to the next day, and I cross the whole thing out if it has become irelevant. It’s also important to note that I strictly adhere to using only one line for each task, as a way to keep it brief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../images/DailyLogExample.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Example of what some daily logs could look like. Taken from the Bullet Journal website.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The core of my bullet journal is the “daily log” (you can read about these in the link I provided above). Before diving into my science, I start each day by reviewing my bullet log from the previous day, mark anything that I forgot to mark, and then transfer the incomplete events to my new day (I use the marking rules I mentioned above). I then add to the list as things come up, and mark them as complete when I get them done. I also use the monthy log to mark major events on the calendar, and major tasks that I need to complete (I’ll even include things like paying rent as a task for each month).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the bullet journal approach is &lt;strong&gt;modular&lt;/strong&gt;, you can also use a future log for planning tasks far in advance. You can also break your tasks and daily logs into dedicated sections. Honestly I don’t use the future log or the indexing/collection approaches because I have not found them helpful for me. While I only use the daily and monthly logs, I encourage beginners to start with all sorts of different module approaches and seeing what works for you. The cool thing about the bullet journal is the room it leaves for you to find what works best in your life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One valuable aspect of this method is actually &lt;strong&gt;writing the tasks and records down in a notebook by hand&lt;/strong&gt;. By writing the tasks down by hand, I have found the practice to stick in my mind more clearly and to ultimately being more meaningful. So what notebook should you use? I think the dotted grid notebooks work great, but you can use whatever works best for you. I have used dotted grid notebooks that I got from vendors at conferences (Nanopore has some good ones), but I also like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Dotted-Grid-Notebook-Journal-Premium/dp/B0797P84CZ?ref_=fsclp_pl_dp_1&quot;&gt;this notebook that you can buy on Amazon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the authors of the Bullet Journal method point out, &lt;strong&gt;mindfulness is key to the approach&lt;/strong&gt;. This is not only an exercize in keeping track of our tasks for the day, but is also an opportunity to reflect on what we accomplished yesterday, what we can accomplish today, and what we need to prioritize for tomorrow. I have also found this to be tightly linked to the practice of forcing ourselves to rewrite the tasks we didn’t complete, as we migrate them from the yesterday to today. Sure it takes a couple minutes, but time is well spent on thinking about whether it is important, and what can be done to complete it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately I have really found the Bullet Journal method to be a game changer in my life and in my science. I feel more confident in my ability to acomplish tasks because I have them recorded effectively, and the daily exercize in mindfulness really helps me prioritize my tasks and think about what I am spending my time on. Hopefully is was helpful for me to share some of my experiences in this post, and I genuinely hope this helps you both organize your life and reflect on what you are spending your time on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, please leave any questions, comments, or concerns in the comment section below. I always love hearing from readers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Organization" /><category term="Science" /><category term="Topic Review" /><summary type="html">Science demands organization, and that's not easy. I've found the bullet journal approach to be really helpful.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Biosynthetic Potential of the Oral Microbiome in Dental Caries and Periodontitis</title><link href="http://microbiology.github.io/blog/oral-microbiome-bgc/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Biosynthetic Potential of the Oral Microbiome in Dental Caries and Periodontitis" /><published>2019-04-21T21:15:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-04-21T21:15:00-04:00</updated><id>http://microbiology.github.io/blog/oral-microbiome-bgc</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://microbiology.github.io/blog/oral-microbiome-bgc/">&lt;p&gt;Understanding and elucidating the links between the microbiome and human health is a complex problem, largely due to the complicated webs of interactions between members of the microbiome and the human host. One layer of this complicated system is the functionality of bacteria within the microbiome. Small molecules, often produced by microbial biosynthetic gene clusters (BGCs), are an avenue many groups are now taking to further elucidate this functionality. As &lt;a href=&quot;http://microbiology.github.io/blog/bgc-transcript-pnas/&quot;&gt;we discussed in this blog before&lt;/a&gt;, BGCs are clusters of co-localized genes that together encode the “machinery” needed to produce small molecules that can impact functionality of either human cells or other microbial cells. In this blog post we will discuss &lt;a href=&quot;https://mbio.asm.org/content/10/2/e00321-19&quot;&gt;the recently reported work of Aleti &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, in which they reported an analysis of the biosynthetic potential of the oral microbiome, and its association with oral disease. The group’s disease focus was on periodontitis and dental plaques, which are significant disease burdens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To study the biosynthetic gene clusters in the oral microbiome, the researchers generated a database of 461 oral bacteria reference genomes and used the &lt;a href=&quot;https://antismash.secondarymetabolites.org/#!/start&quot;&gt;AntiSMASH&lt;/a&gt; infrastructure to identify BGCs within those genomes. The majority of BGC classes were unsurprisingly unclassifiable, although the group was able to infer classes of some of those BGCs by aligning them to the BGCs within the &lt;a href=&quot;https://mibig.secondarymetabolites.org&quot;&gt;MiBIG database&lt;/a&gt; of 1400 reference BGCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;div style=&quot;vertical-align:middle; text-align:center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../../images/BGC-network-analysis-oral-microbiome.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;75%&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Networks were used to identify and visualize similarities between the MiBIG BGC reference database and BGCs predicted from bacterial reference genomes.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once their BGC reference set was complete, the scientists curated a dataset of metagenomic (DNA; functional potential) and meta-transcriptomic (RNA; functional gene expression) information from saliva and dental plaques of 294 subjects who were either healthy, had dental caries, or periodontitis. Alignment of the metagenomic and meta-transcriptomic sequences to the BGC database allowed the group to identify differentially abundant/expressed BGCs between the disease states. The group was also able to follow up with some metabolic analysis (using &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liquid_chromatography–mass_spectrometry&quot;&gt;LC-MS/MS&lt;/a&gt;) to find and validate some signals in the microbiome. Finally, a co-abundance network analysis revealed numerous correlations between BGCs and bacterial taxonomic groups. Most correlations were negative, which the authors suggest reflects antagonistic antimicrobial BGC relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an interesting study that highlights the prevalence of BGCs within the oral microbiome, and the association of those BGCs with oral disease states. The specific disease-associated BGC classes will likely inform hypotheses for the field (these details are beyond the scope of this blog post and can be read in the original manuscript). This paper is particularly notable for how it sets up future studies. In addition to predicting BGCs from reference genomes, it would valuable for future studies to apply the supplemental approach of predicting BGCs from &lt;em&gt;de novo&lt;/em&gt; assemblies from the metagenomic data. Additionally, it would be good to focus on the BGCs that are associated with other interactions beyond those with bacterial taxa. BGC associations with host functions and other microbes, such as fungi, would offer a new level of understanding to the complex system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This manuscript was published in the journal mBio and is therefore open to be read by anybody (&lt;a href=&quot;https://mbio.asm.org/content/10/2/e00321-19&quot;&gt;find it here&lt;/a&gt;). It is a quick read and could be a useful reference if you are in this field, so go ahead, download it, and check it out. As always, if you have any questions, comments, or concerns, please don’t hesitate to drop me a note in the comment section. Thanks for reading!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Recent Research" /><category term="Microbiome" /><category term="Molecular Biology" /><category term="Natural Products" /><category term="Metabolomics" /><summary type="html">A recently reported study outlines the biosynthetic functional potential of the oral microbiome.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bacterial Small Molecules Provide Defense Against Their Viruses</title><link href="http://microbiology.github.io/blog/phage-chem-defense/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bacterial Small Molecules Provide Defense Against Their Viruses" /><published>2019-01-06T21:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-01-06T21:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://microbiology.github.io/blog/phage-chem-defense</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://microbiology.github.io/blog/phage-chem-defense/">&lt;p&gt;Bacteriophages (viruses that specifically infect bacteria) are important mediators of human health. The approach termed &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phage_therapy&quot;&gt;phage therapy&lt;/a&gt; involves the use of phages to therapeutically to kill antibiotic resistant bacteria and thereby treat resistant, life-threatening infections. These phage-based approaches are also appealing in applications such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5609231/#mbt212783-bib-0021&quot;&gt;“microbiome sparing” therapies&lt;/a&gt; for infections, which means the specific infectious bacterium is killed by the phage and the overall community is impacted less than by an antibiotic treatment. For these reasons, it is important for us as a field to understand how phages infect their hosts, and how bacteria evade phage infections. A recently published manuscript by Sarah Kronheim &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt; addresses our knowledge gap of how bacteria combat phage infections by outlining a previously understudied chemical-based bacterial defense mechanism against phages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work of Kronheim &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt; began with an observation in the scientific literature from decades in the past (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/pdf/10.1080/00021369.1979.10863874&quot;&gt;here is a link to one of them&lt;/a&gt;). That past work noted that bacteriophages were inactivated by bacterial &lt;a href=&quot;http://microbiology.github.io/blog/bgc-transcript-pnas/&quot;&gt;secondary metabolites&lt;/a&gt;, which were otherwise of medical interest because of their anti-tumor and antibiotic properties. Although the past groups published their findings, they did not follow up with their work and provide a more comprehensive understanding of the small molecule mediated phage defense mechanisms. Kronheim &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt; picked up where the past groups left off, and provided a more comprehensive understanding of those understudied mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;div style=&quot;vertical-align:middle; text-align:center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../../images/chem-phage-old-paper.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Work from Morita et al in 1979 provided some initial insights into the impact small molecule drugs have on phage infection.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kronheim group began their study by performing a small molecule screen to identify which compounds inhibited phage infection of bacteria (the small molecules were largely products of biosynthetic gene clusters, and some represented FDA approved drugs and bioactive molecules). The approach is illustrated in the &lt;strong&gt;figure below&lt;/strong&gt;, which is from the original publication. The screen was successful and the group identified a subset of small molecules that prevented phage infection of their bacterial host (&lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt;). In addition to their lab strains, the group confirmed that their observation could be reproduced with phages isolated from nature. They also confirmed that the small molecule inhibitors were produced by the bacteria by testing their media. Together this supports the relevance of their observation, and suggests that the small molecules are biologically relevant outside of the lab system and are actually produced by bacteria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;div style=&quot;vertical-align:middle; text-align:center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../../images/chem-phage-screen.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;75%&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Illustration of the group's experimental screen setup, from their manuscript. Bacterial isolates (E. coli) were either cultured alone, with phages, or with phages and a small molecule compound. The growth curves were measured to determine which compounds prevented bacterial destruction from phages.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand the mechanism by which the small molecules were operating, the group characterized the molecule functionality and identified them as intercalating agents. They further found that one of the molecules, daunorubicin, acted early in the infectious process, likely after injection of phage DNA into the bacterial cell, but before replication of that DNA. As was reported in the previously existing literature, this was specific for dsDNA phages, although it was observed across diverse phage families. Further work will be required to more completely characterize the underlying mechsnisms of this system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall this study is broadly applicable and we could imagine myriad directions and implications for the work. I am particularly interested in the implications this work will have for human microbiome studies, including both bacterial and viral communities. I wonder whether small molecule drugs or drug candidates having an impact on the microbiome through this mechanism of bacteriophage infection inhibition? I also wonder what implications this could have in our understanding of antibiotic resistance with different antibiotic drugs. Perhaps some antibiotics are more adept to inhibiting bacteriophage infections, and thereby further limit the potential for spread of antibiotic resistance genes through transduction (both generalized and specialized). And how are these metabolites linked to altered viromes, which are themselves associated with disease? There is a lot of opportunity for impactful and interesting future work from this study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper was short, clear, and overall well written so I suggest you check it out (&lt;a href=&quot;https://rdcu.be/bcAgw&quot;&gt;find it here&lt;/a&gt;). The link should be open access, and was very kindly provided by the authors for sharing. I also recommend checking out the older paper that I linked above in the second paragraph, because it is interesting to get a baseline historical perspective on this most current work. Finally if I missed something, got it wrong, or if you have some other cool ideas, let me know in the comments, Twitter, email, or telegraph. I always love hearing from you and really appreciate any additional feedback or insights.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Recent Research" /><category term="Phages" /><category term="Virome" /><category term="Molecular Biology" /><category term="Natural Products" /><summary type="html">A recently published study outlines a chemical mechanism for phage infection defense in bacteria.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Recent Publication: The Colorectal Cancer Virome</title><link href="http://microbiology.github.io/blog/recent-crc-virome/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Recent Publication: The Colorectal Cancer Virome" /><published>2018-12-15T17:10:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-12-15T17:10:00-05:00</updated><id>http://microbiology.github.io/blog/recent-crc-virome</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://microbiology.github.io/blog/recent-crc-virome/">&lt;p&gt;This year has shaped up to be a busy but exciting year, and one of these exciting parts has been the opportunity to publish some of my work in the human microbiome/virome space. A couple of weeks ago our research group (from when I was at the University of Michigan) had our colon cancer virome preprint fully published in mBio, and I am really excited to see it out. For this post I want to highlight that work and provide a little extra commentary about how I think it fits in the field and where the work is going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our recent paper was titled “Diagnostic Potential and Interactive Dynamics of the Colorectal Cancer Virome” and is freely available &lt;a href=&quot;https://mbio.asm.org/content/9/6/e02248-18&quot;&gt;here on the mBio website&lt;/a&gt;. Briefly, we resequenced a frozen archived stool sample set from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://cancerpreventionresearch.aacrjournals.org/content/canprevres/early/2014/08/06/1940-6207.CAPR-14-0129.full.pdf&quot;&gt;previously published paper from the same lab&lt;/a&gt;. The original Zackular study utilized 16S rRNA shotgun sequencing, but we went back and performed shotgun metagenomic sequencing on both the whole stool as well as VLP (virus-like particle) purified stool. We found that altered viral communities were associated with the cancer state, and that this signal was dominated by bacteriophages (bacterial specific viruses). The bacteriophages were not associated with particular pathogens such as &lt;em&gt;Fusobacterium nucleatum&lt;/em&gt;. This observation was interesting, but how do we interpret an association between bacteriophages and colon cancer?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;div style=&quot;vertical-align:middle; text-align:center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../../images/hannigan-mbio-F6-large.jpg&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;80%&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The final working hypothesis from our study. These panels summarize our thoughts on the results and represent interesting future directions.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are different ways in which the bacteriophage communities could impact colorectal cancer progression, and we outlined some of those in a working hypothesis diagram (see figure above). Based on our findings and previous publications, we hypothesize the phages may be indirectly impacting colorectal cancer progression by contributing to the bacterial community dynamics. The bacteriophages could be causing the initial shifts in bacterial community composition, which in turn contribute to initial cancer progression. The phages could also be contributing to the cancer-associated biofilm dynamics and structure, as well as bacterial lysis and nutrient availability. It is interesting to consider these results in the context of previous literature that outlines the impact of different antibiotics on colorectal cancer progression. Because phages can also kill bacteria, they may impact cancer progression through a similar mechanism as what was observed in the different antibiotic treatments. There are many exciting and important directions in which this work can be taken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At approximately the same time we published this work out of preprint, the group of Nakatsu &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt; published another study which also looked at the gut virome association with colorectal cancer (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0016508518304797&quot;&gt;paper can be found here&lt;/a&gt;). This work offers some interesting additional perspectives to the underlying biology of our system. A big caveat to comparing the two studies is that the group used whole shotgun metagenomic sequencing (no VLP purification) and targeted their bioinformatics analysis toward virus reference genomes. This was unlike our Hannigan &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt; paper that performed VLP purification and more of a &lt;em&gt;de novo&lt;/em&gt; analysis approach. Despite the differences between the studies, both identified significant gut virome signatures associated with colorectal cancer, and together they provide compelling evidence for a role of the gut virome in colorectal cancer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only am I excited about the work our group recently published, I am also very excited about the work coming out of other research groups and the overall direction of the field. In addition to these types of sequencing studies, I expect to see some follow up “mechanistic” work to address hypotheses like those we outlined above. Like other areas of microbiome research, I also expect to see future work begin to study signatures associated with microbes such as fungi or maybe even archaea. This will continue to be an interesting and medically important field to watch.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Recent Research" /><category term="Colon Cancer" /><category term="Virome" /><category term="Microbiome" /><category term="Bioinformatics" /><category term="Computational Biology" /><summary type="html">Our recent publication, as well as others, support a role for the gut virome (specifically bacteriophage) in colorectal cancer.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Microbiome Natural Product Biosynthesis and Synthetic Orphans</title><link href="http://microbiology.github.io/blog/bgc-transcript-pnas/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Microbiome Natural Product Biosynthesis and Synthetic Orphans" /><published>2018-09-23T21:30:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-09-23T21:30:00-04:00</updated><id>http://microbiology.github.io/blog/bgc-transcript-pnas</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://microbiology.github.io/blog/bgc-transcript-pnas/">&lt;p&gt;Wow, it’s been about six months since my last post and a lot has been happening! Between pushing through some papers and working on exciting projects in my new job in pharma, it’s been a busy summer. Unfortunately the blogging took a back seat but I’m excited to hop back onto the computer and hopefully keep the posts more frequent moving forward. So let’s dive in!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the exciting aspects of human microbiome research has been the continued improvment of &lt;strong&gt;functional analysis&lt;/strong&gt; of the communities through techniques such as metagenomics and metatranscriptomics. One approach to understanding microbiome functionality, which has recently been gaining more traction in the field, has been bacterial &lt;strong&gt;biosynthetic gene clusters (BGCs)&lt;/strong&gt;. This focus was especially apparent at recent microbiome/microbiology conferences, including the Beneficial Microbes conference and ASM Microbe conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BGCs are co-localized gene clusters within bacterial genomes that together encode the machinery necessary for synthesis of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Secondary_metabolite&quot;&gt;secondary metabolites&lt;/a&gt;. These metabolites have been widely used as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Natural_product&quot;&gt;natural product drugs&lt;/a&gt; and represent an important area in which the microbiome could be impacting its host. Additionally, bioinformatics techniques have been continuously developed to identify these signature clusters, and those techniques are starting to be utilized with microbiome datasets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;div style=&quot;vertical-align:middle; text-align:center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../../images/pnas.1714381115fig06.jpg&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;One cool concept the paper mentions is the use of Operational Biosynthetic Units for evaluating diversity of the functional potential.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although we can use bioinformatics tools to identify BGCs within bacterial genomes, there are still many challenges in the field. One of these major challenges is that a majority of BGCs remain &lt;strong&gt;orphans&lt;/strong&gt;, which means they have yet to be linked to their secondary metabolite products. A recent paper by Amos &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;, published in PNAS and titled &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/29229817&quot;&gt;Comparative Transcriptomics as a Guide to Natural Product Discovery and Biosynthetic Gene Cluster Functionality&lt;/a&gt;, used transcriptomic and metabolomic approaches to provide important insights into orphan BGCs. This week will review some of the highlights from this study and briefly discuss the impact on the human microbiome field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The core of the paper focused on four strains of the bacterium actinomycete &lt;em&gt;Salinospora&lt;/em&gt;, marine bacteria which contain high numbers of BGCs. The group started by addressing the question of whether orphan BGC products are undetectable due to transcriptional silence (inactivity) in the laboratory. By performing global transcriptomic analyses (identification of which BGCs are active at the RNA expression level) and pairing it with metabolomic analysis (identification of metabolites, including BGC-produced secondary metabolites) at both stationary and growth phases, the group revealed an interesting phenomenon. While many BGCs were active at the gene transcript level (and therefore not silent), the BGC products (secondary metabolites) were still not readily identifiable. Although some orphan BGCs are the result of transcriptional inactivity (gene silence), this result highlights the important limitations of the other detection techniques such as LC/MS techniques, and the importance of understanding the transcriptional activity of the system being studied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;div style=&quot;vertical-align:middle; text-align:center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../../images/pnas.1714381115fig03.jpg&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Comparison of bacterial strain genomes and their transcription profiles revealed other genomic elements whose presence influences BGC expression.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group followed up on this finding by investigating why some BGCs were differentially expressed between the bacterial strains. In other words, why was the same BGC transcriptionally active in one strain and not another highly similar strain? In one notable example, the group found that one orphan BGC was expressed when it included an activator (araC) upstream of the core BGC operon, and was silent when the activator was replaced with a different gene. This is an especially important result because it highlights our potential ability to use additional genes, such as upstream transcriptional activators, to predict which highly similar BGCs will be expressed in related bacterial genomes. This would be a valuable bioinformatics tool for informing the study of the human microbiome, as well as natural product drug discovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall this is a very interesting paper with a lot of insights into BGC activity and regulation. But why is this important from a human microbiome perspective? As a lot of groups in the field have already identified, BGC identification techniques from metagenomic datasets of the human microbiome offer an opportunity to identify largely unrecognized functional potential of the communities. The approach also offers implications for natural product discovery from such microbiome datasets. This paper further highlights the importance of integrating transcriptomic and metabolomic analyses into such studies, so that a more accurate observation of the community activity can be achieved.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Recent Research" /><category term="Natural Products" /><category term="Genomics" /><category term="Bioinformatics" /><summary type="html">Discussion of a recent study that provides new insights into orphan biosynthetic gene clusters, and the implications of those findings for the human microbiome.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Three Technologies With a Future In Computational Biology</title><link href="http://microbiology.github.io/blog/com-bio-tech/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Three Technologies With a Future In Computational Biology" /><published>2018-03-18T17:15:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-03-18T17:15:00-04:00</updated><id>http://microbiology.github.io/blog/com-bio-tech</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://microbiology.github.io/blog/com-bio-tech/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Computational biology is an exciting and diverse sub-field of biology that includes designing algorithms, exploring the human genome, making sense of the human microbiome. Even outside “computational biology”, all sorts of biologists are using computational approaches more and more, including performing analysis in R and processing data using custom Python scripts. At the heart of these computational applications are many powerful and wide-reaching technologies including programming languages (R and Python), code management tools (GitHub and BitBucket), and others. Because it’s always good practice to strive for the best in all aspects of our research, I want to spend this post reviewing some very powerful and promising technological tools that are poised to make large positive impacts on computational biology, as well as the field of biology in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;docker&quot;&gt;1. Docker&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.docker.com&quot;&gt;Docker&lt;/a&gt; is a wildly popular computing platform that allows users to build specialized virtual environments (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.docker.com/what-container&quot;&gt;containers&lt;/a&gt;) that run a program of interest, regardless of the operating system or permissions. Do you want to run a Linux-only program on a Windows machine? Docker allows for that by enabling you to run the program in a temporary Linux environment (the container). Want to run a program on your high performance compute cluster but don’t want to deal with root access and system administrators? Go ahead and run it as a Docker container. Want to easily port your software with its associated reference databases? Containers can contain data in addition to the programs, so go ahead and include the reference in the same place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://tr4.cbsistatic.com/hub/i/r/2016/10/18/831f017c-ee68-4bd6-8a5c-ab31b4d35d6d/resize/770x/1cedcf2f03388a9720835a628a8a9765/dockerhero.jpg&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially Docker provides researchers total control over the programs they are running by allowing them to run those programs in small virtual environments that they completely control. Because each container image is custom built on top of a bare-bones operating system like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ubuntu.com&quot;&gt;Ubuntu&lt;/a&gt;, the processing is incredibly light-weight and efficient (unlike virtual machines). In addition to Docker, there is a server-friendly sister platform called &lt;a href=&quot;http://singularity.lbl.gov&quot;&gt;Singularity&lt;/a&gt;, which provides an efficient and secure way to use Docker in a high performance computing environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I predict Docker is going to impact how we think about and conduct the computational processes around our biological research. A group of biologists have already started a project called BioContainers, which provides container images for many common biological analysis tools. Developers are continuing to make their programs available as Docker images as well, making usage as easy as typing &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;docker pull&lt;/code&gt; instead of installing myriad dependencies and navigating permission issues. I expect to see this more and more in biological research, and you should definitely check it out. It could probably enhance your own research as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;julia&quot;&gt;2. Julia&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://julialang.org&quot;&gt;Julia&lt;/a&gt; has been an up-and-coming programming language over the years. Julia could be described as a powerful analytical language, similar in many ways to R and even Python. Julia is open source and offers simple syntax, insane speed and efficiency, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/JuliaLang/IJulia.jl&quot;&gt;notebook environment&lt;/a&gt; (Jupyter interactive environment), nice data visualization tools, and a growing set of resource packages. Its increased adoption in some pockets of machine learning and biological research, in addition to the other offerings, make it poised to become a go-to language for biologists in the near future. This is a language worth reading about and incorporating it into your own work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;div style=&quot;vertical-align:middle; text-align:center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://biojulia.net/Contributing/latest/assets/logo.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reproducible-documents&quot;&gt;3. Reproducible Documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Us biologists have been observing an ever-growing enthusiasm for reproducible research, especially around the code we use in our published work. Every year more papers are publishing their code, and each year more journals are requiring code to be published with manuscripts. Not only does publishing code allow research results to be reproduced, but it also empowers others to implement similar analytical approaches. Apart from the altruistic enticements, reproducible code practices facilitate faster and more efficient research, increase confidence in the quality of the research, and provide cleaner work environments with less confusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is really more of a theme than a technology, but it made the list because the unifying &lt;strong&gt;Reproducible Research&lt;/strong&gt; “platform” coming out of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.riffomonas.org/reproducible_research/&quot;&gt;Pat Schloss lab&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.protocols.io&quot;&gt;protocols.io&lt;/a&gt;, and others, is a technological resource that is ready to make a big impact on how biologists perform their research. I highly recommend checking this out and implementing some reproducible research practices in your projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Docker, Julia, and the reproducible research platforms are not really new, but are all starting to improve the way computational and other biologists are doing their research. They are poised to make even larger impacts in the near future. These are technologies that are worth reading about, and even incorporating into research projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did I leave something out, get something wrong, or do you have a question? Leave a comment below! I always love hearing from readers! And as always, thanks for reading!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Topic Review" /><category term="Programming" /><category term="Reproducible Research" /><summary type="html">An overview of three technologies poised to make big impacts on the field of computational biology.</summary></entry></feed>
