<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://microbiology.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://microbiology.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-02-23T10:34:55-05:00</updated><id>http://microbiology.github.io/</id><title type="html">Prophage</title><subtitle>The Blog for Bacteria, Phages, Computers, and Science</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Uncovering the Hidden Viruses of Your Urine</title><link href="http://microbiology.github.io/blog/urine-virome/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Uncovering the Hidden Viruses of Your Urine" /><published>2018-02-14T20:15:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-14T20:15:00-05:00</updated><id>http://microbiology.github.io/blog/urine-virome</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://microbiology.github.io/blog/urine-virome/">&lt;p&gt;It’s no secret that the human microbiome (the collection of bacteria, viruses, fungi, etc that inhabit the human body) has provided unprecedented insights into human health and disease. By beginning to understand the complementary roles that these microbial communities play in parallel with our human body, we are seeing many diseases with new perspectives. These new perspectives are already beginning to inform promising new therapies for truly terrible diseases (i.e. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clostridium_difficile_infection&quot;&gt;Clostridium difficile infections&lt;/a&gt;). Although the microbiome consists of fungi, viruses, archaea, and other microbes, bacteria are by and large the most studied component of the human microbiome. The human virome (the viral component of the human microbiome) is understudied, but especially interesting because it consists primarily of bacteriophages (bacterial viruses), which are capable of modulating bacterial metabolism, function, and community composition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../images/PhageIsolatesUrine.png&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many human anatomical site viromes have begun to be studied (gut, mouth, skin, lung). To date, the virome of the urinary bladder, another medically important body site, remains understudied. To address this large knowledge gap, a research group led by Taylor Miller-Ensminger &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;, in the lab of Catherine Putonti at Loyola University, recently published a unique characterization of the human urinary virome using culturing and sequencing techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the authors pointed out in &lt;a href=&quot;http://jb.asm.org/content/early/2018/01/10/JB.00738-17.abstract?sid=839a52cb-ad17-4837-bcc6-73fc91d46a53&amp;amp;abspop=1&amp;amp;related-urls=yes&amp;amp;legid=jb;JB.00738-17v1&quot;&gt;their manuscript&lt;/a&gt;, previous studies have detected viruses in urine microbiome using &lt;a href=&quot;http://prophage.blogspot.com/2013/11/standing-on-shoulders-of-giants-brief.html&quot;&gt;shotgun metagenomic techniques&lt;/a&gt; (a standard microbiome characterization approach). What makes this work of Miller-Ensminger &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt; unique and valuable is that they focus on identifying the prophages (those phages whose genomes are integrated into bacterial genomes) of the urine microbiome. This is valuable because it provides more information about the types of phages present in the urinary tract, and also gives information on what bacteria are likely to be infected by phages. The group accomplished this by culturing/isolating bacteria out of a human cohort and sequencing the isolate genomes. And in case you were thinking about &lt;em&gt;contamination&lt;/em&gt;, they used isolated from mid-stream urine collections, as well as aseptically collected with a transurethral catheter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group ended up with 181 genome assemblies from their collection of isolates, and they identified 226 high confidence phages integrated into those genomes. They were also able to isolate one of their phages out of their samples (see image above). In the end the group added a valuable survey of the lysogenic phages of human urine, and a reference of phages that are linked to their hosts. As the authors mention, this work is especially exciting because it will provide valuable reference material for future studies of the urine microbiome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;div style=&quot;vertical-align:middle; text-align:center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../../images/UrineViromeHostPhyla.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Phylogeny of the bacterial hosts that were used for identifying prophages.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One interesting next step that I could envision would be to use the isolate prophage genome sequences with the previous urine metagenomic studies, or perform shotgun sequencing on the samples. It would be interesting to look at the ubiquity of those phages in other sample sets by aligning shotgun metagenomic reads to the prophage sequences. It would also be cool to use a similar approach to start understanding how many of those phages are actively replicating (or maybe only active in disease states). There are a lot of interesting directions for this work and I am excited to see the next study from the group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall this is a very nice paper that is easy to follow, so I suggest &lt;a href=&quot;http://jb.asm.org/content/early/2018/01/10/JB.00738-17.abstract?sid=839a52cb-ad17-4837-bcc6-73fc91d46a53&amp;amp;abspop=1&amp;amp;related-urls=yes&amp;amp;legid=jb;JB.00738-17v1&quot;&gt;checking it out&lt;/a&gt;. Their data is also published, so it might be worth integrating the sequences into your own future studies. And of course, please leave me a comment below if you have any questions, comments, or concerns. I always love hearing from readers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Phage" /><category term="Microbiome" /><category term="Virome" /><category term="Recent Research" /><category term="Health" /><summary type="html">A group recently isolated bacteria to better understand viruses hiding in bacterial genomes.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Write Your Next Letter Using Markdown</title><link href="http://microbiology.github.io/blog/cover-letter-template/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Write Your Next Letter Using Markdown" /><published>2017-12-31T08:10:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-12-31T08:10:00-05:00</updated><id>http://microbiology.github.io/blog/cover-letter-template</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://microbiology.github.io/blog/cover-letter-template/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markdown&quot;&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://rmarkdown.rstudio.com&quot;&gt;RMarkdown&lt;/a&gt; are great tools for writing scientific documents and manuscripts. Markdown is advantageous over platforms like Microsoft Word because it only uses a simple text file, it allows the writer to focus on content and not formatting, and it can be incorporated easily into reproducible science workflows (Markdown is a sort of code). My colleagues and myself have really enjoyed using Markdown in &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SchlossLab/Hannigan_CRCVirome_mBio_2017&quot;&gt;our own work&lt;/a&gt;, although the documents have primarily been research manuscripts. As I was preparing these types of manuscripts for submission to journals, I wanted to include a Markdown cover letter to accompany my Markdown manuscript. In this blog post I want to present the resulting cover letter Markdown template that I came up with and used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went through two steps to get the template together. The &lt;em&gt;first&lt;/em&gt; was searching around and getting a base template on which I could build. This always makes the process of coding anything a lot faster and easier, although I unfortunately lost the original source, so I’m leaving out an important citation. The &lt;em&gt;second&lt;/em&gt; step was re-writing portions of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.latex-project.org&quot;&gt;Latex&lt;/a&gt; template (the template used for formatting the Markdown file). I modified the template to be highly customizable within the Markdown file, without the need to further modify the complicated template code. I also included an executable shell script to automatically render the final PDF using Pandoc. The resulting PDF will include a header with author information and institute logo, the current data, a signature, and affiliation(s), all of which are easily specified in the Markdown text (remember to include back-slashes before special characters like parentheses). An example of the resulting document is included below, as well as the Markdown text used to create that document.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-markdown highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;---&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;11pt&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;draft&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;no&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;head&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;address&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;123&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;Research&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;Ave,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;Science&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;Building&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;2'&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;city&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;Cambridge&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;state&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;MA&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;zip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;02114&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;phone&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;\(121\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;555-2234'&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;fax&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;\(999\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;555-6565'&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;email&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;hannigan@gmail.com'&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;dept&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;Microbiology&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;Bioinformatics&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;sig&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;include&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;yes&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;sign&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;yes&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;Geoffrey&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;Hannigan,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;PhD'&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;post&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;Bioinformatics Scientist&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;secondpost&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;Distinguished Second Appointment&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;---&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\t&lt;/span&gt;oday

To the editors of Science:

We submit for your review: &quot;The role of the microbiome in health and disease&quot;
by Geoffrey Hannigan and colleagues. We believe this work to be especially
well suited for publication in Science and highly relevant to a broader
scientific readership as well as the general public.

Our lab strives to set high standards of reproducibility and transparency,
while generating and publishing high quality data. As such, all analysis
work-flows, scripts, and datasets have been made publicly available for other
researchers to utilize.

The data presented in this manuscript are original and the manuscript is not
under consideration elsewhere. A preprint version of this manuscript has been
made available through BioRxiv.

We thank you for your consideration and look forward to your response.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../images/ExampleCL.png&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The resulting template is now available as a GitHub repository for anyone to use. You should be able to simply pull the repository, change the example files to meet your needs, and render the manuscript. I do rely a lot of user feedback with these things though, so if you find ways to make it easier to use, please let me know by creating an &lt;em&gt;issue&lt;/em&gt; on the GitHub page. Additionally, please feel free to let me know what you think about this topic and blog post in the comment section below. Happy writing friends!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Microbiology/PandocAcademicCoverLetter&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GO TO THE MARKDOWN REPOSITORY&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Useful Resources" /><category term="Pandoc" /><category term="Markdown" /><category term="Reproducibility" /><summary type="html">Focus on Your Letter Centent by Writing in Markdown and Converting to a PDF Using Pandoc.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New Insights Into How Bacterial Viruses Access The Human Body</title><link href="http://microbiology.github.io/blog/phage-barrier-function/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Insights Into How Bacterial Viruses Access The Human Body" /><published>2017-11-24T15:08:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-11-24T15:08:00-05:00</updated><id>http://microbiology.github.io/blog/phage-barrier-function</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://microbiology.github.io/blog/phage-barrier-function/">&lt;p&gt;The human microbiome, the collection of microbes that live in and on the human body, has continued to gain attention as an important influencer of human health and disease. To date, the majority of microbiome studies have focused on bacteria, but microbiomes are actually complex communities that consist of fungi, archaea, viruses, and of course bacteria. The bacteriophage (viruses that infect bacteria) component of the human microbiome is of particular interest to human health because of the profound influence bacteriophages have on bacterial community composition and functionality. As an example, phages facilitate bacterial virulence in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CTXφ_bacteriophage&quot;&gt;Cholera&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://web.uconn.edu/mcbstaff/graf/Student%20presentations/EHEC/EHEC.html&quot;&gt;enterohemorrhagic E. coli (EHEC)&lt;/a&gt;. Despite their importance, we are still just scratching the surface into how phages interact with the human body to impact health. By understanding these phage - bacteria - human interactions better, we can better understand how the microbiome impacts human health, and how we can create microbiome-based therapies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i0.wp.com/phelix.info/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/xcf.jpg?resize=1154%2C902&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; /&gt;
A recent study led by Nguyen &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt; provided some really cool new insight into how bacteriophages interact with their human body host. In their paper &lt;strong&gt;“Bacteriophage Transcytosis Provides a Mechanism To Cross Epithelial Cell Layers”&lt;/strong&gt;, published in mBio, the group described a mechanism to explain how phages access the human body, and consequently show up in unexpected “sterile” areas like blood and various organs. This is important because it provides insight into how phages might be interacting with the human body, despite their inability to actually infect human cells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The heart of the study was an experimental setup involving &lt;em&gt;apical&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;basal&lt;/em&gt; incubation chambers that were separated by a controlled human cell layer, as is outlined in their figure below. The group started by adding phages to either side of the membrane layer and showed that they could collect phages from the other side of the membrane. The fact that fewer phages could be collected from the apical side than basal suggested directionality to phages’ transportation. They ran this experiment with cells from the gut, lungs, liver, and brain, and observed the same degree of phage transport across the epithelial layer. They also made these observations using a variety of bacteriophages. The group followed up on these experiments with some very cool and extensive microscopy and molecular experiments to confirm that the observed phage transportation was mediated by transcytosis potentially through the Golgi apparatus. Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;http://mbio.asm.org/content/8/6/e01874-17.short&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;paper itself&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for more of those details (it’s open access, so anyone can check it out).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../images/BarrierPhageSetup.png&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; width=&quot;75%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the authors pointed out, this is not the first time someone has demonstrated a mechanism by which bacteriophages could directly interact with human (eukaryotic) cells. Longtime reads will remember that we actually discussed an article in a &lt;a href=&quot;http://prophage.blogspot.com/2013/05/the-bacteriophage-as-vaccine-platform.html&quot;&gt;Prophage post&lt;/a&gt; about phage uptake into eukaryotic cells as a mechanism for gene delivery. Other mechanisms have included phage transport across damaged epithelial tissue, and even “Tojan Horse” phages that enter an epithelial cell by hiding in a bacterium that is engulfed. The novel aspect of this current paper is that they provide comprehensive and detailed information around the mechanism by which phages cross the epithelial cell layer by transcytosis, which allows them to access other parts of the body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course the next question is what these findings mean for human health and the microbiome/virome. A person’s mind could go wild speculating on the different ways that this mechanism could tie into human immunology, disease progression, etc, and these implications for future research are what make the paper especially exciting. However it is important to remember that these findings were done in cell culture (&lt;em&gt;in vitro&lt;/em&gt;) and things could look very different in a real human system. It will be incredibly exciting to watch how this line of research progresses, but for now I think it’s a good idea to temper our expectations on how this is going to impact human health and disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this all sounds cool, I would suggest checking out the &lt;a href=&quot;http://mbio.asm.org/content/8/6/e01874-17.short&quot;&gt;manuscript online&lt;/a&gt;. It’s even open access, so it’s super easy to get the document. It’s a nice read and the authors really do present a lot of interesting data. And as always, let me know if I missed something or if you have a question, comment, or concern. Let me know in the comments below. Otherwise you can find me on Twitter, reach out by email, etc. I always love hearing from readers! :)&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Phage" /><category term="Microbiome" /><category term="Virome" /><category term="Recent Research" /><summary type="html">Bacteriophage Transcytosis Provides a Mechanism To Cross Epithelial Cell Layers</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Whole New Blogging World</title><link href="http://microbiology.github.io/blog/hello-world/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Whole New Blogging World" /><published>2017-11-18T14:13:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-11-18T14:13:00-05:00</updated><id>http://microbiology.github.io/blog/hello-world</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://microbiology.github.io/blog/hello-world/">&lt;p&gt;Hello and welcome to the new Prophage blog site. If you’ve read the blog before, you know that the site used to be hosted by Google Blogger &lt;a href=&quot;http://prophage.blogspot.com&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Prophage was active for many years and accumulated well over 100,000 views! It’s been exciting, but the old format was starting to get restricting. In an effort to deliver more and better designed content, I decided to make the switch to a GitHub hosted blog using &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.hoosier-realtors.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/moving-tips.jpg&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; width=&quot;40%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The switch came at a good time, following a hiatus I took from blogging. In the past few months, I have been working to finish up a couple papers from my postdoctoral fellowship at Michigan, while also moving to Boston to start a new position in industry instead of academia. I joined the new &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.merck.com/about/featured-stories/cambridge-mrl.html&quot;&gt;Merck Exploratory Science Center&lt;/a&gt; in Cambridge and am very excited to be working on some super cool science!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will certainly keep updating the blog as it grows. Right now I am using an &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mmistakes/so-simple-theme&quot;&gt;awesome, open source theme&lt;/a&gt; to get started, but I will probably start customizing that as I move forward. I also don’t have my old blog posts transferred over, but that is something else that I am going to work on. For now, you can still see the &lt;a href=&quot;http://prophage.blogspot.com&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;old blog posts here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading, and keep an eye out for some more awesome blog posts on the new site! :)&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Welcome to the new Prophage blog site.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://microbiology.github.io{&quot;feature&quot;=&gt;nil}" /></entry></feed>
